<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An answer to Dr. Burgess his book, entituled A case concerning of buying bishop lands which he spread before the Parliament, wherein he goes about to justifie that tythes is the ministers of the gospels maintenance.</title>
            <author>Fox, George, 1624-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 84 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40115</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1743</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R30466</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11326423</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11326423</idno>
            <idno type="VID">47471</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40115)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 47471)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1460:48)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An answer to Dr. Burgess his book, entituled A case concerning of buying bishop lands which he spread before the Parliament, wherein he goes about to justifie that tythes is the ministers of the gospels maintenance.</title>
                  <author>Fox, George, 1624-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 44 [i.e. 36] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Simmons ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: G.F.</note>
                  <note>Numerous errors in pagination.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Burges, Cornelius, 1589?-1665. --  Case concerning the buying of bishops lands.</term>
               <term>Tithes.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:47471:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:47471:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANSWER To Doctor <hi>Burgeſs</hi> his Book, entituled, <hi>A Caſe concerning of buying Biſhop Lands which he ſpread before the Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein he goes about to juſtifie, that Tythes is the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Goſpels maintenance.</p>
            <p>In which anſwer it is plainly ſhewed, how that tenths was the maintenance of the Prieſts under the Law, and for the relief of Widdowes, ſtrangers and fatherleſſe, and not the maintenance of the Miniſters of the Goſpel, who was in Chriſt the power of God, which brings people out of the Earth. And how Tythes was ſet up by God, in the time of the War, and in the time of the Law, ſince man was drove from God into the earth, and the ſeed came into the earth? And how that Chriſt (by whom the World was made) redeems men (out of the Earth, and ninths, and ends tenths) up to God, (who is the heir of all things) who ends the war and the Law, and brings peace on earth, and good will towards all men.</p>
            <p>Moreover it is here ſhewed, how the Law ſerved but until the ſeed came: And that the Miniſters of Chriſt did not run with a ſtore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe to gather up tenths, but they brought people out of the ninths of the earth, and trode out the corn, here the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction was known before the World began.</p>
            <p>It is alſo ſhewn how the Tythes that now are, have been ſet up by the Papiſts, the Apoſtates ſince the dayes of the Apoſtles, and ſince the true Church fled into the Wilderneſſe, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.</p>
            <p>And this is to be delivered to each Parliament man to be read over, and they may ſee that in it which they never ſaw before: and for all people it may be profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to read.</p>
            <p>The ſtrength of the Doctors arguing for Tythes, anſwered, according to the Scripture, and overturned by <hi>G. F.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>London, Printed for <hi>Tho. Simmons,</hi> at the <hi>Bull</hi> and <hi>Mouth,</hi> near <hi>Alderſgate,</hi> 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:47471:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:47471:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Doctor BURGESS his Principles for Tithes, <hi>pag.</hi> 7.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>FIrſt, That Tithes are the proper maintenance ſet out by God, for the Miniſters of the Goſpel, and cannot be alienated, (or taken away) without ſacriledge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly, Tithes are due by Divine Right to Ministers of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Page 8. <hi>That all yearly Tithes of Cattel, Fruit, and of all things elſe are still due by Divine Right to Christ, and by him are given to his ſervants the Ministers of the Goſpel, and may not be alienated; his proof,</hi> Numb. 18.26. When ye take of the children of Iſrael the Tith<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> which I have given you from them for your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, &amp;c. Hence he chargeth with Sacriledge ſuch as detaineth either of theſe from the Prieſts and Levites, as robbers of the Lord, of Tithes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And</hi> Abraham <hi>paid Tithes to</hi> Melchizedeck, <hi>the tenth of the ſpoil to the high Priest of God, at least in Tipe, for Christ himſelf is a Priest for ever, after the ſame Order, who hath the ſame Right to Tithes as</hi> Melchizedeck <hi>had.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore all yearly Tithes are the proper standing maintenance ſet out by God for the Miniſters of the Goſpel, in all ſetled, well-grounded, Christian Common Wealths: which in the obedience to God, made laws for the due payment of them, for they still belong to Christ as his Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and Portion, payable to his Ministers by way of homage, as Right from all his people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And to put them to any other uſe is Sacriledge, not onely in thoſe who aliene, (or are ſtrangers) from them, but alſo in them who poſseſs and imploy them, if they be not Ministers of Christ, and preach not the Goſpel, or procure ſome other, if themſelves be ſick or diſabled to do it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>It being no other but robbing of Christ, of what is his proper due, and by God made Holy to himſelf;</hi> page the ninth.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:47471:3"/>
            <p>ANSWER, FIrſt, All Tithes hath been ſince the fall, ſince man was drove from God, and hath been out of his Image, he being drove from God into the earth; ſo Tithes hath been ſet up ſince the beginning, ſince man hath been in the earth.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Abraham</hi> paid Tithes to <hi>Melchizedeck,</hi> the King of Righteouſneſs, the Prieſt of the moſt High God, out of the ſpoil, when he came from the ſlaughter, who met him with bread and water. But it is not ſaid that <hi>Melchizedeck</hi> took of the ſpoil of all Wars, but once of <hi>Abraham;</hi> and it is not ſaid, he took Tithes of <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſubſtance, or of every mans ſubſtance, nor of any other mans ſubſtance, as I may ſo ſay; <hi>Levi</hi> paid Tithes, yet in the loyns of <hi>Abraham,</hi> who afterwards received Tithes; And <hi>Levi</hi> the Prieſt received Tithes in the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and ſo the Prieſthood made by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of God, had a Command according to the Law of God, to take Tithes of the people.</p>
            <p>And there was Tithings out of Tithes, and this was not given to <hi>Moſes</hi> the chief Magiſtrate (as the chief Magiſtrate now takes the Tenths of Tenths, which the Pope was the firſt Author of: and ſince, them that denies the Pope, which takes the Tenths of the Tenths) Where did you read that the chief Prophet, or chief King among the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> did take them?</p>
            <p>So then Tithes before the Law to <hi>Melchizedeck</hi> (the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude and figure of Chriſt, in the time of the War, from <hi>Abraham</hi>) and Tithes in the time of the Law to the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, made by the Law of God, who had a Store-houſe to put it in for his ſervices.</p>
            <p>And the Widows, Strangers, and Fatherleſs did not want, There was not a beggar amongſt them, they were all filled and ſatisfied.</p>
            <p>And they that did not bring their Tithes, they robbed God, as Chriſt ſaid to the Phariſees, <hi>Ye pay Ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he of Mint, and Annis, and Cummin, theſe things ought ye to have done;</hi> (Mark, to have done) This was before Chriſt was offered up, the Everlaſting
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:47471:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>Prieſthood, he ended the Prieſthood that took the Tithes, and diſannulled the Commandment that gave them, and changed the Prieſthood alſo that took them, and is the end of all ſimilitudes and figures, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.</p>
            <p>And in him <hi>Melchizedeck</hi> ends, who took them in the time of the War, and there is no figure in Chriſt which ends the War; who brings peace on earth, and good will towards men, and ends the offerings, and ends the Ninths and Tenths, and Redeems man out of the earth, out of Types, figures and ſhadows, and ſimilitudes; that he may live and ſee where he needs no figure, ſhadow, nor ſimilitudes, and Redeems man from under the Law, and ſo out of the ninths as well as the Tenths.</p>
            <p>And ſo who comes to Chriſt comes to Subſtance, out of the earth, out of the ninths, as well as the Tenths, and knowes the Election before the Foundation of the World was: for the Tenths was offered up in the time of the figure and ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude, in the time of the War, in the time of the ſpoil the Tenths was offered up, in the time of the Law, of the increaſe of the earth, and of the ſpoil before the Law.</p>
            <p>But the time of the Goſpel, the time of Chriſt, the Ninths is offered up by them that come into the power of God, as well as the Tenths; and ſo man comes to be Redeemed from the earth up to God, from whence he was driven, and to reign upon the earth, and made Kings and Prieſts, and the War comes to be ended, and figures, and the Law comes to be ended, <hi>Christ is the end of the Law for Righteouſneſs ſake to every one that believes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For Ninths and Tenths in the time of the War, and in the time of the Law, was in the times of the figures; and ſince man hath been drove into the earth from God, that God by his Law Commanded they ſhould offer up the Tenths: but who are Redeemed again out of the earth, and come to Chriſt the Subſtance, and is come up into the Image of God, and is come into the Goſpel which is the power of God; comes out of the Ninths of the earth, and offers up all, and ſo comes up into Chriſt, the Image of God, the end of the Law, the Heir of all things.</p>
            <p>And ſo while the Prieſthood was ſtanding, <hi>Levi</hi> who w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:47471:4"/>receive Tythes before he was offered up, and ſo they ought to pay him, but when he was offered up, it was finiſhed; ſo when he was offered up, people were to come to the ſubſtance and to ſeek thoſe things that are above, and not the tenths in the war, which <hi>Melchiſedeck</hi> the figure received, nor the tenths in the Law, which the firſt prieſthood received, but muſt offer up the ninths, and all, to Chriſt who is the heir of all things (him by whom the World was made, glorified with the Father before the World began) who redeems man out of the earth, and ſo man comes to preach the Goſpel, the Word, which was in the beginning, and ſo comes into that which ends all things, that is Chriſt, who is the Heir of all things, who redeems his Church; and who are of his Church, are of the Election which was before the World began.</p>
            <p>And ſuch as preacheth the Goſpel, the Kingdom of God, was to go without bag, that Chriſt ſends forth, and he never ſet up a law that they ſhould take the Tenths; for it was the Prieſthood that was before Chriſt that took the tenths; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore read this what it ſignified, that Chriſt ſent forth his, free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, without bag (his Miniſters) and the other Prieſts muſt have the Tenths, made by the Law of God, and had a command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to take them, and he ſent out his freely, and <hi>Melchiſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deck</hi> had tenths in the time of the war; but Chriſt who ends the Law, ends the war, and deſtroyes the Devil and his works, which is the cauſe of all war and ſtrife, ſends forth his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters freely, reely you have received, freely give again.</p>
            <p>Now the Jews Law was ſtanding when Chriſt ſent forth his Miniſters, by which the Prieſthood was made, and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement was not diſſanulled till Chriſt was offered up; ſo Chriſt did never claim (to the Jewes) that Tythes was his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, for he who redeems man out of the earth, is the heir of all things, for Tythes was offered up in the time of the law, &amp; war, <hi>Melchizedeck</hi> and the law brings people to offer up the tenths; and that was according to the principle of God in them, But Chriſt brings them to offer up the ninths, as wel as the tenths, the ninths of the earth, and ſo comes out of the earth quite, to the ſubſtance Chriſt Jeſus, and ſuch knowes the election before the world began, &amp; Chriſt the heir of all things.</p>
            <p>So he is not called the heir of tenths, he is not called <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chizedeck,</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:47471:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>neither is he called the firſt Prieſt-hood that took the Tythes, but is called the ſubſtance of all Types, figures, ſhadowes, and ſimilitudes, and is the heir of all things, and ends the Prieſt-hood that had the tenths, and is an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Prieſt, after the order of <hi>Melchizedeck,</hi> who was glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified with the Father before the World began, before the tenths was.</p>
            <p>So he ends the figures, and all figures, and tenths, and Tythes, that redeemes people out of the ninths; and ſo the Church of Chriſt which is his body, of whom he is the head, in whom he is in the mideſt, who was in the beginning with the Father before the world began, ſeeks not after the tenths, who redeems out of the ninths, who brings to the end of the law, and end of the war, and all types and figures, and ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, and ſimilitudes to Chriſt the ſubſtance, and ſuch wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe peace on earth, and good will towards men, and the Kingdom come which ſtands in joy, and righteouſneſſe, and peace in the Holy Ghoſt, and his will is done in earth, as it is in Heaven.</p>
            <p>So till Chriſt was offered up, Tythes was to be paid, and they robbed God that did not pay Tythes; while Tythes was kept back, there was not meat in their houſe, and ſo God kept back from them; you keep back the tenths, cannot I keep back the ninths, and cauſe the earth not to give her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe; ſo bring in your Tythes, and ſee if I will not cauſe the windowes of Heaven to be opened, and pour you forth a bleſſing, that there ſhall not be room enough to receive it.</p>
            <p>And the Tythes of the land was the Lords, it was not to be given to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> it was not called <hi>Caeſars,</hi> the tenths was the Lords, and he gave them back to the ſervices, for which he appointed them; and this was the State, when man was drove into the earth in the time of the law.</p>
            <p>Now the ninths is the Lords as well as the tenths, and all the ſpoil in the war is the Lords, as well as the tenths, to <hi>Melchideck,</hi> the figure; ſo in the time of Chriſt who ends the war, all is offered up unto the Lord, all the ſpoil, the ninths, the time of Chriſt, the end of the law, and Prieſt-hood that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:47471:5"/>took the tenths, the ninths is offered up, and they come out of the ninths of the earth, ſo to Chriſt the ſubſtance, who redeems out of the ninths, and ſuch comes to reign upon the earth, as I ſaid before, and be made kings and Prieſts: And there is more to be ſpoken of theſe words hard to be uttered.</p>
            <p>And Chriſt never told people they robbed him, that did not bring him the tenths, who was the everlaſting Prieſt, though the Jewes law was yet ſtanding before he was offered up; he ſpoiled principalities, and powers, and triumphed over them openly, and put down Prieſt and its authority, and tenths and its authority, and brought people to the beginning, out of the ninths to the Father, and to fit with him in Heavenly places.</p>
            <p>And the Church never told people that it was robbery if they did not give them tenths, and Chriſts Miniſters never ſaid it was robbery, though the Jewes law was ſtanding, when they went to preach freely without a bag, when Chriſt the power of God ſent them forth, which power opened the hearts of people to give them, that they ſhould not want, and they trod out the corn.</p>
            <p>And the Jews law was ſtanding, and the Prieſts, and tenths, before Chriſt was offered up, and Chriſts Miniſters, and preachers of the Goſpel never complained to the Jewes, or went to the Jewes, which had the Law of God, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of God, which gave the tenths, that they ſhould (by the commandment) give them the tenths, but they preached Chriſt freely, by whom the world was made, the wiſdom of God, the Saviour of the world, that ends all types, figures, and ſhadowes, and changeable things, and other Prieſts, and redeems out of the ninths, to live in the word, and power of God, that lives and abides, and endureth for ever, which all things are upholden by, by the word, and power, which gives every thing its being, and encreaſe, and meat in their due ſeaſon.</p>
            <p>And theſe preached Chriſt, and followed him which was the ſubſtance, and never looked down to the time of the war, for tenths, nor to the time of the law for tenths, but preached him that was the end of the war, and law, and brought peace on earth, and good will towards men; and theſe ſat in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:47471:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>heavenly places with him, and minded not earthly things, but were Redeemed out of Ninths as well as Tenths, and knew the Election before the World began, and come into Paradice, and to know Paradice, and to know the Garden whence man was drove out of, into the earth, out of the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of God, out of the earth, into the Image of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and ſo in the Garden; ſo, do they follow Chriſt who lives in the Ninths of the earth, or not? Chriſt never claimed the Tenths in the time of the War, nor in the time of the Law, though <hi>Melchizedeck</hi> that figure, and Prieſts had them; but Chriſt is the end of all figures.</p>
            <p>And the Jews Law was ſtanding in the dayes of the fleſh of Chriſt when he was upon the earth; but when he was offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up it was finiſhed, who went to his Father where he was before the World began, who ſaith, follow me who is the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of Salvation.</p>
            <p>The young man in the Goſpel which had kept the Law, he would offer up the Tenths; but he muſt offer up the ninths, that is a hard thing to ſell his poſſeſſion, he is a rich man, he would be willing to pay the Tenths; well this is but a touch of what might be ſpoken concerning theſe things.</p>
            <p>The Church of Chriſt which is the Election in Chriſt, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the foreknowledge of God, before the World be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan, which are Redeemed from the earth, and reigns upon the earth, as Kings and Prieſts; that witneſs the end of the War; and before War began, and before the fall was: in the Image of God, in the Dominion over all the Creatures, in the Wiſdom of God, in the Power of God, and the end of the ſpoil, and to the end of the Law, and Prieſts that took the Tenths in the Law, and witneſſeth the diſannulling of the Command and Prieſthood both: ſuch be in Chriſt, ſuch be the Church, and ſuch doth not claim Tenths, that be in Chriſt, the Heir of all things, (mark that word) that Redeems out of the Ninths, for as I ſaid before in the time of the Law, and the War, the figure, like unto the Son of God, was Tenths paid, but in the time of the Goſpel Ninths given up, yea, all is given up to the Lord, and the earth is the Lords, and the fulneſs thereof.</p>
            <p>And them that believe in Chriſt be in the Wiſdom of God,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:47471:6"/>and ſo the Church never claims the Tenths which was in the time of the War, or Law, who are come into the Goſpel, the Power of God, which ended the War, and Redeemed from under Law; and they never told people that they were rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſt, that did not pay him the Tenths, and that it was his inheritance, which was the firſt Prieſthoods, and Chriſt ends the firſt Prieſthood which had the Tenths: and ends the War, and Redeems people out of the Ninths to himſelf, who is the Heir of all things: Glory to him for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</p>
            <p>And ſo Tithes doth not belong to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> but to God, and ſo doth Ninths too, for ſince man was drove from God, the Commandment was, Thou ſhalt offer up the Tenths: but as men ſhall come to be Redeemed from under the Law to God, they come out of the Ninths of the earth and offer up all to God (for the Law ſerved until the ſeed came) and ſo can ſay, all is the Lords, and comes out of the earth again, and reigns upon it, which is Gods foot-ſtool, and Heaven his Throne; ſo mark, men being drove from God into the earth; Ninths in the time of the Law, and in the time of the War, and the firſt Prieſthood, and <hi>Melchizedeck</hi> the ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude, after that Order came, Chriſt, who Redeems men a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to God out of the earth, as he was drove from God into the earth, fell from his Righteouſneſs and Image, by tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion and diſobedience; ſo by the obedience of Chriſt who is the Image of God, is man again brought to God, out of the earth: ſo out of the Ninths, and ends the firſt Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood that had the Tenths, and the Law by which they were made, and the Commandment diſannulled that gave them, and ends the War, and the Tenths, and the ſimilitudes; he who is after the order of <hi>Melchizedeck,</hi> Prieſt of the moſt High God, who yet liveth, who ends in Chriſt, who is the Heir of all things; and many more things I have to ſpeak, which is as yet hard to be uttered, to this.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Levi</hi> paying Tithes in <hi>Abraham,</hi> and Chriſt who came to end the Levitical Prieſthood, is yet a Parable to all, but who believe in Chriſt, who was before <hi>Abraham</hi> was, or <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chizedeck</hi> took the Tenths of the ſpoil which was ſince the fall, for Chriſt ends the War, who is the Heir of all things (Mark,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:47471:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>all things) which is more then Tenths, and takes all, and reconciles all things in Heaven, and all things in earth, in one, that deſtroyes the Devil and his works, and his things, and ſo doth not reconcile to thoſe things, the Devils things, but deſtroyes him and his things, and he that deſtroyes him, and his things and works, reconciles all things in one: Things in Heaven and things in earth, ſo doth not reconcile to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs but deſtroyes that which cauſes it, and ſo brings into Unity with God, and one with another, who is the Word, and Power, who is called the Sanctification, and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification: and more is to be ſaid in this, which as yet is hard to be uttered.</p>
            <p>So Tithes was due by Gods Law to his Prieſthood, which was made according to his Law, which had a Command ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Law to take them, and Chriſt is the end of the Law to every one that believes, and thoſe that believe are his Church; Marke here, Whether thoſe that are the Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers goes into the Tenths? And whether or no they are come to Chriſt who Redeems out of the earth, and ſo are come out of the Ninths of the earth to God, through his I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage Chriſt Jeſus, who is the brightneſs of his Glory, and the expreſs Image of his Subſtance? Chriſt Jeſus who was with him before the World began, as I ſaid before.</p>
            <p>Well, ſeeing that Chriſt ended them that had Tenths in the time of the Law, and War, and ended the War and Law, by which they were made that took them, and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment that gave them, to them, and ends the War, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Law, and is the end of all Wars: who puts the fire, and the ſword in the earth: and deſtroyes the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyer, that cauſeth Wars: and brings peace on the earth, and good Will towards men: and his Miniſters preacht the Goſpel and the Kingdom of God, which hath no end, (Mark, the Kingodm of God, there is more in that) that followed Chriſt, that they preacht: and asked not for Tithes, for Tenths of the earth: that was Elected before the World began, that was Redeemed out of the Ninths, that witneſſed the Kingdom of God that ſtands in Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Peace, and Joy in the Holy Ghoſt, and that ſit in heavenly places in Chriſt Jeſus; And you may read what
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:47471:7"/>they witneſſed in the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> among them that ſtuck in the Figures, Prieſts, Tithes and Offerings, which told them that the one offering was offered up, the end of their offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and Prieſthood both, that could not continue becauſe of death, and Chriſt was come, the end of all ſimilitudes, he remains a Prieſt for ever after the order of <hi>Melchizedeck;</hi> and the Prieſthood was changed that took the Tithes, and the Law was changed, and the Commandment diſannul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led: ſo when the Prieſthood was changed, and the Law changed that gave them, and the Commandment diſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulled, and men come up out of the Ninths to the heavenly gift, and did partake of the power of the World to come, and yet theſe things was but as milk among Babes.</p>
            <p>Before Chriſt was offered up, they ought to pay Tithes, but when he was offered up, then they ought not, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment diſannulled, the Prieſthood changed, the Law changed alſo, Was ended, peace on earth, and good will towards men: Election known before the World began, and men Redeemed to God from the earth, who had been drove from God into the earth: who had loſt his Image by tranſgreſſion and diſobedience, who is brought into the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage by the obedience of Chriſt, who blots out the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, and finiſheth ſin, and reconciles for iniquity, and brings in Everlaſting Righteouſneſs, (Mark, Righteouſneſs laſteth for ever) that Redeems men out of the Ninths, and ends the War, in whom <hi>Melchizedeck</hi> the figure ends, and liveth not in the Righteouſneſs of the Law of works, of the Prieſts that had the Tenths, and Command, that Commands the Tenths, but lives in Chriſt, and by him, and under him, who is the Treaſure of Wiſdom and Knowledge, that ends the Command, and Law, and Prieſthood, and War, and Figures, and in him doth <hi>Melchizedeck</hi> end, Chriſt who is the end of all things, and here is the Saints life, and the Churches head, that the gates of Hell cannot prevail againſt, who is the ſum of all things, that ends Ninths, and Tenths.</p>
            <p>And his Church is Redeemed out of the Ninths and reigns upon the earth, and preaches the Goſpel, the Kingdome of God, (Mark, Kingdom) and preaches the Subſtance, the end
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:47471:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>of the ſimilitudes, the end of the firſt Prieſthood; the Law is changed that he was made by, and he alſo, and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand diſannulled that gave him Tithes, and here the peace on earth, and the good will towards men is known; for Chriſt is the Peace and Redeemer, and now he is come to reign, and doth reign among his Saints, who ends all ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litudes and likeneſſes, and in him is no ſhadow, nor turning, nor winding, nor variableneſs, who is the Image of God, glorified with the Father before the World began.</p>
            <p>For ſince man went out of the Image of God, and his Righteouſneſs, has been the Wars, the firſt Prieſthood, and the Tenths in the War, and the Tenths in the firſt Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and Figures, which Chriſt the Image of God ends the War, and Prieſthood, and figures, and ſimilitudes, and Tenths, and brings men up into the Image of God, and his Righteouſneſs, and Redeems people out of the Ninths, and ſo to the end of the Tenths, and Warre; being come out of the fall up to God again, where peace is, redeemed out of the earth, and reigns upon it, and there is the end of that at preſent; and ſo much for that at the preſent.</p>
            <p>And Tenths was paid from the Principle of God within them, for man tranſgreſſing the Principle of God within him was drove from God, but when the Law came which went over all tranſgreſſors, and tranſgreſſions, &amp; anſwered the juſt Principle of God in every man, the Tenths was offered up in the time of the War, and Law, from the Principle of God within, and ſo is the Ninths from the Spirit of God within, the power of God, the Goſpel, and where life and immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality is come to light, all is offered up to God: And man come up out of the earth unto God from whom he has been drove.</p>
            <p>And from the Principle of God within, he did offer up the Tenths according to Law; for death reigned, man tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſing the Law of God within him, when he fell, went from the power.</p>
            <p>The Devil went out of truth, tempted man out of truth, to ſin, and ſo to death, and death reigned from <hi>Adam</hi> till <hi>Moſes,</hi> and ſo the Law came by <hi>Moſes,</hi> who ſaw the firſt tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion upon the earth: and ſo the law was added becauſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:47471:8"/>of tranſgreſſion, which is called the higher power higher then all evil doers, to which power every ſoul muſt be ſubject.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaw the bleſſed ſtate of the creatures before tranſgreſſion, before the Divel and man went out of truth, and ſo man had the power within him before the tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the power within him, the law within him, and ſo the law was added upon him, called the law of works, becauſe of tranſgreſſion, and that ſerved tell the ſeed came; and <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaw the Prophet of God, he knew that the ſeed of the Woman ſhould bruiſe the head of the Serpent; Chriſt Jeſus ſhould deſtroy the Devil and his works, the ſalvation of mankind.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Moſes</hi> the Prophet, God gave him that wiſdom, to make the pattern, the figure, and <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaw the time it ſhould ſtand, and before it was; and the Prophet God ſhould raiſe up like unto him, whom the people ſhould hear, who ſhould come to end it.</p>
            <p>Now he that can read this, and ſee this, and hear this prophet which ſhould end the pattern, types, figures, and ſhadowes, may read ſomething; and he that hath offered up the ninths of the earth, and is come out of the ninths, by Chriſt the ſubſtance, redeemed out of the earth, and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth ſin and tranſgreſſion finiſhed, and the bond of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity broken, and Chriſt reconciled to him, and everlaſting righteouſneſſe brought in, he witneſſeth the end of tenths, and may ſpeak ſomething of what the tenths figured forth, and offerings, and Prieſts, that witneſs the ſeed, and is in the ſeed Chriſt, that hath bruiſed the head of the Serpent, (the Divel that cauſeth war) he may ſay, a ſtronger then he is come that keeps the houſe, and that the ſtrong man has bowed himſelf, and that the keepers of the houſe has trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and the earth ſhaken alſo, and that which is to be ſhaken, ſhaken, and that which cannot be ſhaken is appeared, and Chriſt is in him, and his body is dead becauſe of ſin, and he is the Temple of God, and Chriſt is in him the everlaſting Prieſt, and Chriſt reigns, and the firſt covenant is ended, and the law of works which went upon the man which was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der types, figures, and ſhadowes, to which his ſoul muſt be ſubject; but Chriſt is come, the end of the Law to every one that believes, the Biſhop of the ſoul, Chriſt the power of God,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:47471:8"/>and the everlaſting covenant is within again, and he is come into a greater ſtate then <hi>Adam</hi> was, in the beginning, he is come into the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> into that which cannot depart from God, and all that be here, need not ſay, know the Lord from the greateſt to the leaſt, but are calling every one his neighbour, under the vine, and fig-tree, according to <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charias</hi> propheſie, and the branch is brought forth, and ſtone upon ſtone, and ingravening is taken away.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning Tythes ſince the dayes of the Apoſtles.</head>
               <p>And as for Tythes, ſince the dayes of the Apoſtles, the Pope was the firſt Author of them; for as Chriſt ſaid falſe Prophets ſhould come, inwardly ravening Wolves, having the Sheeps cloathing, that is the outſide in <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.24. chapter, which <hi>John</hi> ſaw was come in his firſt Epiſtle, in chapter the 2. and fourth, which went forth from them into the World, and in the revelations, all that dwelt upon the earth, went after them, and Chriſt who ſaid they ſhould come, bid they ſhould not go after them, and <hi>John</hi> who ſaid they were come, told the Saints that they needed no man to teach them, but as the ſame anointing did teach them which was in them, and as that did teach them they ſhould continue in the Son of God and in the Father.</p>
               <p>So thoſe that Chriſt ſaid ſhould come to his Diſciples, the falſe Prophets, and Antichriſts, <hi>John</hi> ſaw was come (one of his diſciples) which went forth from them into the World; and in the <hi>Revelations,</hi> all that dwelt upon the earth went after them, and when they had got a head in the World, they turned againſt the Saints, and killed the Saints, that kept the Teſtimony of Jeſus. <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.24. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.4 <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.</p>
               <p>And ſo in the eleventh of the <hi>Revelations,</hi> the witneſſes were killed, and in the twelfth, the dragon was wrath with the woman, and ſhe fled into the Wilderneſſe to be kept a time, and times, and half a time, to be fed, and the man-child was caught up to God, and the dragon made war with the remnant of her ſeed; ſo here is the true woman, the true Church fled into the Wilderneſſe, and the Dragon gave his power to the Beaſt, in the thirteenth of the <hi>Revelations,</hi> the Leaſt made war with the Saints, that kept the Teſtimony of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:47471:9"/>Jeſus the ſpirit of Prophecy, the true Miniſters, and killed them, and overcame them, and when he had overcome the Saints, power was given to the Beaſt, over all kindreds tongues, and peoples and nations.</p>
               <p>So he had power over the naturals, Hebrew, Greek and Latin, called the Original, Orthodox men, and killed the true Miniſters which kept the teſtimony of Jeſus, the ſpirit of prophecy; then he having power over all kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds, tongues and Nations, then deceit ſpread it ſelf over all nations, the true Church being in the Wilderneſſe, and the man-child caught up to God; and then came up the Beaſt and his names, markes, and hornes and images, who was in the Dragons, the Devils power, and compelling to worſhip, and ſet up his lying ſignes, and wonders, and has power over the tongues, to order them, here he has his Schooles, and colledges, to order them as he will, the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turals, that killed them that was in the ſpirit.</p>
               <p>And then the Whore got upon the beaſt, the falſe Church, the falſe woman, the Whore, in the Dragons power: after the True Church was in the Wilderneſs, and all Nations drunk her cup of Fornication, before they could be mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried; and the Kings of the earth drunk her cup of Fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Then did the Kings of the earth make Nations to bend, and the ſheeps cloathing to be put upon them, for ſhe hath reigned over the earth: This fenced city, this falſe Church, this Whore, where all the blood hath been ſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Religion, Church, Miniſtry, and Scriptures, in the whole Chriſtendom, among them called Chriſtians, ſince the dayes of the Apoſtles, and Chriſt who wreſtled not with fleſh and blood, ſtruck not at creatures, did not come to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy mens lives, but to ſave them; and the Apoſtles that followed him, wreſtled with Principalities and powers, and ſpiritual wickedneſſes: and brought the creature into the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of the ſons of God.</p>
               <p>And Chriſt deſtroyed the Devil, and his works, and death, which had its authority in men, and yet ſaved mens lives; he did not cauſe any to be put in Priſon, neither did he put any in Priſon, though they Blaſphemed againſt him, nor the Apoſtles neither, but deſtroyed the Devil and his works, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:47471:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>death, where he had his Authority, which cauſed men to Blaſpheme, and ſaved the man: and the Apoſtles wreſtled with ſpiritual wickedneſſes, and rulers of darkneſs, which cauſed men to Blaſpheme; and brought the creatures into the liberty of the ſons of God, and ſuch came to know the Redemption of the body.</p>
               <p>But this falſe church, this great city, this woman, this whore which hath made all Nations drunk with her Fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Kings of the earth, wreſtleth with fleſh and blood, deſtroyes mens lives (if any one come within her city which is fenced) though they have the ſheeps cloathings, yet deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mens lives, ſtocking, whipping, and impriſoning, killing, racking, cutting off ears, wreſtling with fleſh and blood; d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ing the blood of the Saints, killing the creatures in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> wreſtling with principalities, and powers, and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> wickedneſſes, and rulers of darkneſs, in high places, and ſo followeth not Chriſt and the Apoſtles, who are the inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly raveners that went out from them, which is the Whore, for a whore goes from ſomething; the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> when they went from their God, they whored; ſo when theſe went from the Apoſtles, they whored, and all Nations hath drunk the Whores cup.</p>
               <p>And ſo the Inhabitants of the earth which hath drunk the Whores cup, have the ſheep cloathing, but not the ſheeps Nature, (which never worried, ſwine, nor dogs, nor goats, nor lyons, nor bears) ſo inſtead of ſaving mens lives, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed them, and inſtead of bringing creatures into the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of the ſons of God, hath killed the creatures; and this is like neither Chriſt nor the Apoſtles, but quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, out of their power, in the Dragons power, devourers, murtherers.</p>
               <p>And ſo this Whore ſits upon the waters, and the waters are Peoples, Nations, Tongues, and Multitudes, as you may read in the <hi>Rev</hi> 17. and 18. chapters. Now, Mark, Nations are waters, and Peoples are waters, and Tongues are wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Orthodox men which are called the Pillars of the Church, ſhe ſuffered them to live, this falſe church, this Whore which hath drunk the blood of the Martyrs, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and Saints; ſo killed the true Miniſters, and ſo theſe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:47471:10"/>are them that have ſet up their Schools and Colledges, to to make Miniſters, and their Tenths, ſince the dayes of the Apoſtles, who was not of man, nor by man, but by the Will of God.</p>
               <p>And again, the Judgment of the great Whore ſhould come, this falſe church, and the myſtery babylon confounded, and the Beaſt taken, and falſe prophets, and the old Dragon, and caſt into the lake of fire, and the man child brought forth to Rule all Nations with a Rod of Iron, and the Lamb and the Saints ſhall have the Victory; and the Lambs Wife known a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and the Everlaſting Goſpel preacht again to all Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds, Tongues, and Nations, to all that dwell upon the earth.</p>
               <p>What may the Tongues ſay, have we not had the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> all this while? and the Beaſt, and the Dragon, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> prophets, and the Beaſts names, ſeveral images, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is in the Nations, who hath power over all Kindreds, Tongues, and Nations? I ſay no. you that are inwardly ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vened, went forth from the Apoſtles, into the World, you went from the power, and ſo from the Everlaſting Goſpel, which muſt now be preached again to you; and this is hard to be believed with the Tongues, and falſe church, the Whore, as it was among the Jews at the firſt, Going forth of the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>And ſo now the Goſpel is going forth to all Kindreds, Tongues, and Nations, and Life, and Immortality, is come and coming to light, and the Everlaſting Goſpel preached a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain freely, without a Bagg, or Store-houſe for Tithes, which the firſt Prieſthood had. And the thirſt is riſen in people, and to that which they ravened from, is people come and coming, and the Lamb and the Saints ſhall have the Victory; the Bride and the Lambs Wife is witneſſed and ſhall be witneſſed, the True Church is known again, he that was dead is alive, and ſhall live for evermore.</p>
               <p>So all theſe names, and marks, and horns, and Images, and ſeveral Crowns, in the whole Chriſtendom, is among the inwardly raveners, and how ſhould they be otherwiſe, when they ravened from the Spirit of God, in which ſtands the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and Fellowſhip, and Bond of Peace.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:47471:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>So they have ſet up Tithes, which ravened from the Spirit of God, from the Apoſtles; they could not ſet them up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Apoſtles, but went forth from them into the World, and ſet them up there, and the old <hi>Maſs-houſes,</hi> Eaſt, and Weſt, which they call Temples, or Church, with a croſs on the end of it; they went from the Power of God the Croſs of Chriſt, whoſe bodies were not the Temples of God, but the ſynagogues of Satan, the Murtherer: who has killed one another about Church, and Miniſtry: and priſoned till death for Tithes, and haled before Courts, and Seſſions, and Aſſizes: the chief Magiſtrate in many places hath taken the Tenths, of the Tenths, which the Pope was the firſt Author of, ſet up in the World by the beaſts, and Dragons power, and the great Whore, and falſe church, when the True Church went into the Wilderneſs; But as the true Church comes up again, all theſe things are fathomed, ſeen, and felt over, which hath got up ſince the dayes of the Apoſtles; and this is but a touch of what might be ſpoken concerning theſe things.</p>
               <p>And ſo Tithes hath been ſet up by the laws of men, which they have invented, ſince the dayes of the Apoſtles; among them which went from the Apoſtles, for the Apoſtles witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the end of the Law of God, and Commands and Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood that took them, as in the <hi>Hebrews</hi> 7th. chap.</p>
               <p>And ſo theſe that have taken Tithes in the whole Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom by the Law of men, and invention, hath not gone ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Law of God, for they were to have a Store<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe, and all the Widows, Strangers, and Fatherleſs, were to be filled, and eat, that there might not be a begger among them: and this proviſion the Law made, when Tithes was the Lords, the Tenths, and he would make the Ninths ſerve <hi>Levi</hi> the Prieſt, and give him enough, and all Widowes, Strangers, and Fatherleſs; for men was in the unreaſonable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs till the Law came: in falſe meaſures and weights, but Chriſt the end of the Law Redeems men out of the Ninths and the Law anſwers the reaſonable Principle of God in every man, which is Juſt, Holy, Good, and Perfect, ſo the Law goes over all, and lets ſee the firſt tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and goes over all tranſgreſſion, and that is the Higher
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:47471:11"/>power to which the Soul muſt be ſubject, whether in the hand of King, or Supream; and this is not like the Heathens In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions, or Statutes.</p>
               <p>Now the Apoſtles witneſſed the end of the Commandment, that gave Tithes, and the Law, by which the Prieſthood was made that took them. Therefore, they that went forth from the Apoſtles into the World, ſet up Tithes, where there is no Store-houſe for the Fatherleſs, Widowes, nor Strangers, in the whole Chriſtendom; but Prieſt goes away with all, and and it may be, Pope or chief Magiſtrate has the Tenths, of the Tenths; and Widows, and Strangers, and Fatherleſs, crying up and down the ſtreets, and Steeple-houſe doors for bread, at the old <hi>Maſs-Houſe</hi> doors, that it is a ſhame to ſee them.</p>
               <p>Though men talk of the Goſpel, and of the proviſion of the Goſpel, yet they are not come to the proviſion of the Law, that provided to them all, in practice, and life.</p>
               <p>And what haling before Courts, and caſting into Priſons dayly by the Prieſts and Impropriators, for Tithes? And what cryes the people? We muſt give you Tenths, and we muſt be in the Ninths; Are you Miniſters of the Goſpel, and no Store-houſe to relieve the Widows, Strangers, and Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, that there might not be a begger amongſt us? And you cry you have a Law to give it you; but cry the people it is not like the Law of God, that Widows, and Strangers might be filled as well as you; you are them that went forth from the Apoſtles into the World, from the Goſpel, and Law both, of God.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtles preached the Goſpel, and brought people out of the Ninths, to offer up the Ninths, and all, to the Lord; and ſo it ſhall be now, as the falſe prophets Beaſt, and Dragon is taken, and the Judgement of the great Whore is come, and the Everlaſting Goſpel preacht again to them that dwell upon the earth, which was among the Apoſtles.</p>
               <p>People ſhall come out of the Ninths of the earth, not onely the Tenths, but all to the Lord, for the earth is the Lords, and the fulneſs thereof.</p>
               <p>Theſe that hath ſet up Tithes ſince the dayes of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, are them that are inwardly ravened, that went from the Apoſtles into the World, which now by the power of the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:47471:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>Lord God, are comprehended and fathomed.</p>
               <p>So Tithes to <hi>Melchizedeck</hi> in the time of the War, and Tithes in the time of the Law, and all the Tithes of the land was the Lords, and he would make the Tenths of the earth give the Prieſts, Levites, Strangers, Widows, and Fatherleſs enough, and fill them, that there ſhould not be a Begger a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, and the Ninths would give the other enough; and thoſe were offered up according to the Principle of God in people, which anſwered the Law of God; and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment that commanded them.</p>
               <p>Now Tithes ſince the dayes of the Apoſtles, ſet up by them that went from them, inwardly ravened, hath been invented, and not ſet up by the principle of God within; So here is Prieſts, and Impropriators, Kings of the earth, and Pope hath got them; and Widows, and Strangers, and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſs ſtarving abroad; and yet theſe Prieſts will be called Miniſters of the Goſpel, that takes Tenths and keeps peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the Ninths, which they have invented, and their mother, the great Whore, the falſe church, and calls them a Goſpel maintenance, which are not like unto the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, but contrary to the Law and Goſpel both; and all people are nor blind that they cannot ſee.</p>
               <p>For the tenths was offered up in the time of the war, and law, but the ninths comes to be offered up in the end of the war, and law, and types, figures, and ſhadowes, by ſuch as comes to the Kingdom of God; for they that preach the Kingdom of God, and the Goſpel, doth not take the tenths of the earth; and this is but a touch of what might be ſpoken concerning theſe things.</p>
               <p>And ſo Tythes is not the Miniſters of the Goſpels homage, as thou Dr. ſaith, in thy ninth page; for Tythes is not the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Goſpels homage, who brought people out of the ninths; but it was the firſt Prieſt-hoods, which Chriſt the ſecond came to end, and redeems out of the ninths, up to God, out of the earth, for ninths and tenths hath been ſince man was drove from God, into the earth; but the tenths has bin the Popes homage, and held up by his lawes, in the whole Chriſtendom, proviſion for his Church, ſince the dayes of the Apoſtles, that the true Church went into the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:47471:12"/>and his Miniſters, and the inheritance that he hath given to his Teachers, that hath got the Sheeps cloathing, that went forth from the Apoſtles, inwardly ravened, and ſet up firſt by his law, and perſecute people if they would not give them, and put them into priſon till death, and hale them before Courts, which is not the work of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Goſpel, as thou may read in the <hi>Acts,</hi> and <hi>Epiſtles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thou ſayeſt in the ſame page, that to imploy Tythes to any other uſe, then to maintain Miniſters of the Goſpel is ſacriledge, for they are due by God, and holy to himſelf, ſo to give them to any other then Miniſters of the Goſpel, or to ſuch as ſet Miniſters to preach, becauſe they are fick them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and cannot preach, it is ſacriledge to put them to any other uſe.</p>
               <p>So then thou haſt made all the impropriators robbers, and the Pope, and all the chief Magiſtrates, and Kings that take the tenths, robbers, and the great men that takes the Tythes, robbers; now I ſay they have no more due to them, then the Miniſters, nor they, then them, but is quite contrary to the Miniſtery of the Goſpel, to keep people in the ninths, that they might have the tenths, and having no ſtore-houſe for them, that all the ſtrangers, fatherleſs, and widowes, might be filled, as well as the Prieſts, <hi>Deut.</hi> 14 and <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>But if you had ſtore-houſes, and did fill all the Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, and widowes in the whole Chriſtendome, yet we which are Miniſters of the Goſpel muſt deny you, and the firſt Prieſt-hood that took them; we that are one with the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, that brings people out of the ninths, that they may be redeemed out of the earth, up to God, for ſince men was drove into the earth from God, was tenths ſet up by the command of God, which Chriſt the Saviour of the World, redeemes up to God again, out of the earth, for tenths was a figure in the time of the law, and Chriſt, who was made under the law, redeemes from under the law, ends the law, and the figures, and the war, and brings people to reign upon the earth, and ſuch be elect before the World was made, of his Church, of his body, he is the head.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:47471:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Now Tythes which been invented by the inwardly raven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, that went out from the Apoſtles, by the beaſt, falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and falſe Church, ſince the true Church went into the Wilderneſſe, and ſince the true Miniſters hath been ſlain by the Beaſt, and their blood drunk by the whore, and ſo deceit ſpread over all nations; and as the Apoſtles was to go with truth into all Nation, ſo the beaſt, falſe Prophets, and great whore, and old dragon taken and caſt into the lake of fire and their fleſh burnt, and the everlaſting Goſpel ſhall go forth again to all nations, tongues, and people, to all that dwell upon the earth, and ſo truth ſhall ſpread it ſelf over again.</p>
               <p>So mind theſe three ſtates, and what age you are in, that you may decern the time, and ſeaſons which be in the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers hand, how that people ſhall come out of the ninths, and tenths, which has been invented by them, that were inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly raveners, that went forth from the Apoſtles, and how that people are comming to that which they ravened from, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the power of God, the Goſpel is felt, and life, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality is come to light, and the thirſt is riſen among peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who ſhall have the waters of life freely and the marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of the Lamb, the Church is known again, the manchild is brought forth to rule all nations, with a rod of Iron, for they have been waters, and tongues, and multitudes, and that which has been called the original among the inwardly raveners, the tongues, but not called ſo by <hi>John,</hi> nor any of the Apoſtles.</p>
               <p>For all the earth was of one language before <hi>Babel,</hi> and <hi>Pilate</hi> ſet the languages over Chriſt, and <hi>Luke</hi> doth not call that the original, for <hi>Pilate</hi> did not know the Scripture, and the Beaſt, and the whore hath been upon the tongues, which hath killed the Saints, and <hi>John</hi> in the <hi>Revevelations</hi> did not call that the Original, for <hi>John</hi> ſaw well that tongues were waters.</p>
               <p>But they had the Original which was killed by the beaſt, and the whore, and this hath been the language ſince the beaſt, whore, and dragon hath reigned, and the true Church hath been in the Wilderneſſe, and the true Miniſters killed; but I ſhall tell you, in the beginning was the word before
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:47471:13"/>beaſt, falſe Prophets, dragon, great whore, <hi>Pilate</hi> and <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> was; and <hi>Abides</hi> when they all end, when they are not, ſo that I declare unto you that which was in the beginning, the word of life that you might have fellowſhip with the Father, and the Son, and with us.</p>
               <p>And who are in this, are out of ninths, and tenths both, in which all figures, ends, types, and ſhadowes, ends, and by which word, all inventions of men are thrown down.</p>
               <p>And ſo taking away tythes, is but robbing, as they call it, the Popes Church, the falſe Church, which ſet them up, but not according to the Law of God; which was not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Law of God, nor Goſpel, and have not gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them; according to the Law of God, had they done it there had not been a begger in Chriſtendome, for the Law made that proviſion, but the Goſpel is above the Law, which redeemes people out of the ninths, opens the heart of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
               <p>So they are pitiful poor, and ſilly, that are talking of the tenths, in this the day of the Goſpel; the Lambs power, and his marriage, and the comming up of the true Church out of the Wilderneſſe, judging the falſe Church, and great whore which is got up ſince the dayes of the Apoſtles, which hath ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled Chriſts words, and Chriſts words muſt be fulfilled, as in <hi>Mat.</hi> 24. who ſaith every tree that bears not fruit, muſt be hewen down, and caſt into the fire, which ſcripture is ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling, to deſtroy the falſe Prophets, and yet ſave the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, who wreſtleth with the power of darkneſſe, and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual wickedneſſes, and not with fleſh and blood, ſuch have ſpiritual weapons; but they that ravened from the ſpirit of God, loſt the ſpiritual weapons, and ſo got <hi>Caines,</hi> which hath guarded the great whore, which has killed the Saints with <hi>Caines</hi> weapons, <hi>Cain</hi> killed <hi>Abel.</hi> and built a City, and ſo who ever comes into this great City, where nin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> and tenths, and inwardly raveners are, falſe Prophets, great whore, the falſe Church, old Maſs-houſes, they muſt look to have their fleſh and blood wreſtled againſt where the dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons flag, and the whores golden cup is holden forth.</p>
               <p>Now look over whole Chriſtendom, you may ſee what
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:47471:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>hath got up ſince the dayes of the Apoſtles; and what a fenced City here hath been, and how it is fenced, and how the blood of the Martyrs hath been drunk in it (which keeps the Commands of God, and the Teſtimony of Jeſus, which hath the Spiritual) weapons and how many this great Whore hath put to death by her weapons, this falſe church, the Lord open your underſtandings that you may ſee to the dayes of the Apoſtles, who ſaid, that the ages ſhould come that God would ſhew forth the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Riches that was among them, as you may read in the <hi>Epheſians</hi> the ſecond chapter; And theſe ages are come, ſo here is a diſtinction betwixt the Miniſters of the Spirit, and the miniſters of the great Whore, which ravened in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly from the Spirit of God, which hath had the ſheeps cloathing, which beaſt and great Whore hath been in the Dragons power, killing, and murthering, which City hath been filled with violence, and blood.</p>
               <p>But the power of God over all this is gone, over all this is felt, to the dayes of the Apoſtles, what ſtate they were in, and what ſtate hath been ſince, with that we ſee to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, with the Word of God, which was in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doctor</hi> page the ſeventh, Thou ſayeſt thou ſhalt not muz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zle the mouth of the Ox that treadeath out the Corn.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer.</hi> We ſay ſo, where he gets out Corn, not to muzzle his mouth: but let not the Ox eat where he doth not tread out the Corn, let him not tranſgreſs; all this is nothing to Tithes; for we do not read that the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the Prieſts, was to take Tithes of any, but of the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> not of the <hi>Gentiles;</hi> &amp; we do not read that Chriſt ſet up a Law, or the Apoſtles, that they ſhould take the Tenths of the <hi>Gentiles.</hi> but man being drove from God into the earth; A Virgin ſhall bare a Child, which by inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation is <hi>Immanuel,</hi> God with us, and I will give him for a light to the <hi>Gentiles</hi> and for a new Covenant to the houſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and to the houſe of <hi>Judah;</hi> and many of the priſoners have ſhewed themſelves forth, man drove from God, man brought to God again.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doctor,</hi> Let him that is taught in the Word, communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:47471:14"/>to him that teacheth in all good things, <hi>Gal.</hi> the ſixth chapter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> We ſay yes, let him that is taught, do it, but he doth not ſay, he that is not taught; Therefore this condemns all the Prieſts ſince the dayes of the Apoſtles, who would have from them they do not teach, contrary to the Rule of Scripture, and Doctrine of the Apoſtles, and caſt into Priſon thoſe they do not teach, theſe ſerve not the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, but their own bellies, and teach for filthy lucre, which they ought not, who would have all good things communicated to them, from them they do not teach.</p>
               <p>So he that is taught in the Word, communicates to him that teacheth in all good things; Mark this juſt Rule, He that is taught, he that teacheth: ſo every one main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain his own Miniſter, that will have one. And be not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, God is not mocked, for that which you ſow, that you ſhall reap: ſow to the fleſh, you ſhall reap corruption, ſow to the Spirit, life Eternal; and they that are inwardly ravened cannot ſow to the Spirit, but ſows to the fleſh.</p>
               <p>Therefore you may look in whole Chriſtendom, what a Field of corruption there is to be Reaped, and what un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable Miniſters there is, that will bring this Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and ſay, That he that is taught in the Word, let him Communicate to him that teacheth in all good things, when they never taught him; hath not taught him in the Word, yet will have good things Communicated to him; whether theſe be not unreaſonable wolves in ſheeps cloathing, who will take treble Tithes of him, and hale him before Courts, if it be a hundred or two hundred miles, and then caſt him into Priſon: and then bring people the Scriptures for a Cloak, and denying the light within, which they ſhould fee withal.</p>
               <p>So ſuch are tranſgreſſors of the Doctrine of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, which takes of them which they have not taught in the Word, neither do they preach the Word which was in the beginning, which ends the Prieſts that had the Tenths, and wreſteth the Scriptures: and this is nothing to Tenths, and no where Tithes is Commanded in the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:47471:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>New Teſtament, but onely as Chriſt ſaid, ye ought to do it before he was offered up: but when he was Sacrificed up, it was finiſhed, and the Prieſthood that took them, the Law, and Command, they Triumphed over them.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Ananias,</hi> and <hi>Saphirah</hi> makes nothing for Tithes, and Chriſt being hungry, they fed him, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And Chriſt ſent forth his Diſciples without Bag, But what did <hi>Judas</hi> Bag ſignifie? That Steward, that Betrayer? Are not all ſuch as invented Tithes, and ſo greedy after the Bag, of the ſubſtance of <hi>Judas,</hi> that will caſt into Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and betray the innocent in Courts, and take treble of them, going with <hi>Judas</hi> Bag, and eating and drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing damnation to themſelves? mind what <hi>Judas</hi> his Bag figured forth, that betrayer of the Juſt; and mind how all the Miniſters in whole Chriſtendom goes forth now with gold, and ſilver, and purſes, and Tenths, and yet they ſay that Chriſt ſent them: and will not go without it, and have great Parſonages: And mark, who betrayed him, but him that had the Bag; and if Tithes had been Chriſts inheritance, why would he not take them, when upon the earth?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doctor,</hi> If we ſow unto you Spiritual things, it is leaſt if we reap of your carnal things.</p>
               <p>Mark, Here is to you, to you that we ſow too, to you, not to them they did not ſow too; now theſe will take the Compulſion, and Law, and go to the powers of the earth, and take treble Tithes, and caſt them into Priſon, that they have not ſowed Spiritual things too.</p>
               <p>Now if we ſow unto you Spiritual things, it is the leaſt to Reap of your carnal things. I ſay yes, this is to them that are ſowed to: ſo I ſay as I ſaid before, let every one maintain his own Miniſter: ſo the Apoſtle ſaith, have I not power to eat? have I not power to drink? for when Chriſt ſent forth his Miniſters, what was ſet before them, that they might eat, and bid them enquire who was worthy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to what Town ſoever they went; but did not make a bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain with them for their lives time, and compel all to give them means which did hear them, and did not hear them, which they did not ſow too, nor Miniſter too.</p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:47471:15"/>
               <p>He that plants a Vineyard, eats of the fruit of it, keeps a Flock, eats of the milk of it: (Mark here) he hath threſhed, and plowed, and planted, and laboured, and gotten a Flock: But mark, how Chriſtendom lyes like a Wilderneſs, ſow Spiritual, reap carnal, keep a Flock, eat of the milk, ſhalt not muzzle the mouth of the Ox that treadeth out the Corn, ſo they need not go to the powers of the earth; but the Flock will give them milk, and the Vineyard give them fruit, and reap carnal, the Ox meat, and there is no allowing to Magiſtrates which hath made no Vineyards, nor ſowed Spiritual things, nor gotten out the Corn, where they have ſowed Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual.</p>
               <p>Now they reap corruption, which ſow to the fleſh, though they may have taught the people 40 years, yet they ſay, the people are carnal; and ſo run and tell the Magiſtrate with a Petition, that the people are carnal, ſo theſe Teachers were never ſent out by the Father to plant Vineyards; but by the will of men, and ſo ſhames them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and the people both, which are called Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>And though the Apoſtle ſaid, have I not power to eat, have I not power to drink, yet he did not ſay, have I not power to take augmentations, and Tithes, and gleabe lands, and ſtipends, and to take treble Tithes of them, and caſt them into Priſon, that they did no work for, which they have not planted, yet theſe will uſe their power to eat; but the Apoſtle ſaid, he would not uſe his power, but keep the Goſpel without charge, and ſo loſe not his glorying; ſo you have loſt your glorying, and ſo have brought a great charge upon the people ſince the dayes of the Apoſtles, who are out of the Goſpel, the power of God; for if you had been in it, you had brought glad tydings to the Nations; And had not been like Luci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, that makes the World as a Wilderneſs, and opens not the Priſon houſes, but puts them into Priſon; and this may you and Chriſtendom read <hi>Iſaiah</hi> the 14th chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doctor.</hi> So they that ſacrifice at the Altar, were partakers of the Altar, and they that Miniſtred at the Temple, lived
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:47471:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>of the Holy things; they that preach the Goſpel, lives of the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>The Altar and Temple is down, and the Holy things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it, and the Prieſts, and the Tenths, and the Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and Offerings, and they that preach the Goſpel; they live in that which brings people out of the Ninths.</p>
               <p>And had you troden out the Corn in the whole Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom, the Wheat had been up before now above Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption: and had you ſowen Spiritual things, life Eternal had been reaped, and a harveſt before now; And had you been them that preached the Word, you would have been Communicated unto, by them you had taught, ſo that you would not have needed means of others, by ſuch cruel doings: And had you kept the Apoſtles Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and Chriſts, freely received, and freely give, you had been like the Lillies: out of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> ſteps, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other things would have followed, &amp; them that would not have received you, ſhake off the duſt of you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> feet againſt them, like the Apoſtles; and had you planted Vineyards, you might have eaten the fruit: and gotten a Flock, you might have eaten the milk: then you need not have ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vened up and down to Magiſtrates with Petitions, to make them your pack-horſes croaking under them, like the frogs.</p>
               <p>Now Chriſt hath Redeemed people out of the Ninths, if he would have lived in the Ninths, he might have had a hole, and a neſt; but he had not whereon to lay his head; read the Parable; and if you had preacht the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, which opens peoples hearts, you need not carry the Bag, nor provided, but have been as the Lillies; and Chriſt might have had a Store-houſe, to have put his head in, if he had had the Tithes; but he ends Store-houſe, Ninths and Tenths, and brings people to God, to the power from which they were droven.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doctor.</hi> The Labourer is worthy of his hire, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10. <hi>Luke</hi> 22.</p>
               <p>We ſay yes, he that hireth a man is worthy to give him his wages, and the workman is worthy of his meat: he that ſets him at work, is worthy to give him his meat. But
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:47471:16"/>would not Prieſts, and Profeſſors ſay, it was unrighteous for one to come and bring theſe words to him, and would have money and meat of him, which never ſet him on work, nor hired him? Would they not ſay, he was a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of unrighteouſneſs, not according to Law, nor Goſpel, that ſues him at the Law, and caſts him into Priſon, and takes treble of him whom he never hired, nor ſet at work? Is not this the Dragons power, and the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of unrighteouſneſs that do ſo? And is not this Gods power that ſaith, the labourer is worthy of his hire, and the workman of his meat? and it is a juſt thing to give it them; ſo to take meat and hire of them that did not ſet them at work, is not this lying, and bringing the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for a Cloak? And ſaying, they are Miniſters of the Goſpel, and caſt into Priſon till death them that do not give it them, are not theſe Uſurpers?</p>
               <p>And what did <hi>Aunanias</hi> and <hi>Saphirahs</hi> keeping back part ſignifie? and the lyar that lodgeth in the earth, which was overt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>own? Now apply that, and know the appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; for none of the ſcripture doth uphold the Tythes of the Pope, got up ſince the dayes of the Apoſtles, but ſpeaks of things in their place.</p>
               <p>And whether or no theſe actions, and doings, doth not ſhew the falſe Prophets, going with Sheeps cloathing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their backs, and how men are covered with fig-leaves? but now in the light openly ſeen.</p>
               <p>And the <hi>Levites,</hi> and Prieſts, and Widowes, and ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and fatherleſſe, that was to be fed with the tenths, had places to lay their heads in, but Chriſt, which redeems out of the ninths, has none.</p>
               <p>And the Apoſtle gave forth an order to <hi>Timothy,</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> what Miniſters ought to be, muſt be proved, and tryed, they muſt be blameleſſe, and not ſelf-willed, not ſoon an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, not given to wine, no ſtrikers, not given to filthy lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre; ſo then they muſt firſt be proved, and then they muſt Miniſter; for after his diſceaſe, he ſaw that grievous Wolves would enter in, which would be covetous, and teachers for filthy lucres ſake; and the Apoſtles ſaw the perilous time coming on, that men ſhould be lovers of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:47471:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>themſelves, and covetous, this he told <hi>Timothy,</hi> &amp;c. there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore gave an order to prove them, and to try them as you may read, the firſt Epiſtle to <hi>Timothy</hi> 3 chapter, but what ſtrikers are got abroad? blameable men, covetous, greedy of filthy lucre, unpatient, brawlers, brawling in their pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets.</p>
               <p>And ſo if Monaſteries, Abbies, Nunneries, Maſs, even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſongs go down; why not Tythes? Did not he that ſet up one, ſet up the other, by the unrighteous law? And why ſhould the Prieſts, they which be of the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> tribe, wear black coats, but you may ſay people people begins to ſee us, and we will go change our coats, take the means, &amp; deny the work? and when the one falls, why doth not all with it? When the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> fall, why doth not Schooles, and Colledges, Tythes, and Mortuaries, and Glebe-lands, <hi>Easter</hi> reckonings, <hi>Midſummer</hi> dues, the old Maſs-houſes, and the Croſs? Have not theſe the Merchants of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon</hi> made<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Merchandize of people ſouls, of their bodies, Beaſts, Sheep, and all they had? And is not this the whore ſeeing Chriſt came the ſubſtance of all true types, fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures, and ſhadowes, who made all things new, ended the tenths, and Prieſts both, and all fell down with it, when the Law fell, and command fell? And hath not all theſe been the blind guides, which hath been in the Tythes? and the blind leaders, which hath run at peoples, fleſh and blood, and creatures? Who ſhould have run at the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of darkneſſe, and wreſtled with that, and brought the creatures into the liberty of the Sons of God.</p>
               <p>And hath not all theſe that deſtroyes men in priſon, and haleth them before courts, whom they do not work for, have been charmers for their own bellies, and for filthy lucre, and covetouſneſſe, and tenths of people, and keep people in the ninths, &amp; worries the Lambs, like bryars, and thorns, and with their unclean feet uſurp the place of the Apoſtles, who were preachers of the Goſpel, that hath been in the chair of <hi>Judas,</hi> of covetouſneſſe, betraying the juſt? which of them all will prepare themſelves to preach, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out bag, or lucre, in hunger, and thirſt, and faſting, and tents as the Apoſtles did? and be like the lillies, not
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:47471:17"/>take thought what to eat, or what to drink; or to put on, or what to ſpeak, as Chriſt commanded?</p>
               <p>So the reformed Church, the Church indeed, is out of all theſe gleabe-lands, <hi>Easter</hi> reckonings, <hi>Midſummer</hi> dues, &amp; you that go about to reform Churches, it is but to change colour; for the true Church is a Church of it ſelf, which Chriſt ſaith, he is the head of, without ſpot or wrinkle, and blemiſh, purchaſed with blood and ſuch things; for they are got up ſince the true Church went into the wilderneſſe, and are not agreeable to Law, nor Goſpel; and do you not believe that all the Biſhops Lands, firſt ſet up by the Pope, that it was all given for the worſhip and ſervice of God? The Papiſts did believe it, and the Biſhops and Prieſts in <hi>England</hi> did believe it: and the ſame ſet up Tithes, and do you not believe it, that the Prieſts, and Profeſſors doth believe, that the powers of the earth doth give them that, for the worſhip and ſervice of God, which was firſt ſet up by the Papiſts, and not yet plucked down, but upholden?</p>
               <p>For was not that firſt given to the Church, this falſe church, this falſe woman, the whore, ſince the True Church went into the Wilderneſs and denyed by the Church in the dayes of the Apoſtles? <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. hath not all theſe that went forth from the Apoſtles, that inwardly ravened, offered the ſtrange fire? and been in the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the Dragon? out from the Worſhip of God, in the Spirit, not like to worſhip him in the Spirit when inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ravened, ſo ſwallowed up in the earth, <hi>Core</hi> like; for their offering is but as the cutting off a dogs neck, or as if they ſlew a man, being inwardly ravened from the Spirit of God, which ſhould offer up the Spiritual Sacrifice, in which Spirit God ſhould be worſhipped.</p>
               <p>All the whole body of theſe in Chriſtendom, both ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, and Miniſter, and ſetter of them up, which hath been of men and by men, of them owned, and heard, hath not theſe made up a great City, fenced with the weapons of them that are inwardly ravened, who hangs out <hi>Cains</hi> Flag, who are from the Spirit of God, and turneth againſt them that hath the Spirit of God, and killeth them? and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:47471:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>which makes the Word of God of none effect, which has ſet up the Tongues, for the Original which was in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, before the many Languages was.</p>
               <p>And how are all Nations drunk with the Whores cup, and ſick, and vomit, and ſpewing out that which is naught? firſt tranſgreſſion, inwardly ravened, then ſick, and then vomit and ſpew, and then go among the falſe phyſicians; for none comes to the True Phyſician, but they that come to that they were ravened from, and there they find the True Phyſician.</p>
               <p>Did not Doctor <hi>Burgeſs</hi> take Tithes, and gleabe Lands, and Eaſter reckonings, and Midſummer dues? Is he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Biſhops lands, becauſe the <hi>Parliament</hi> hath taken them away? Would he not cry them up to be for the ſervice and worſhip of God, if the Magiſtrate would ſet them up again, and give them thanks?</p>
               <p>And was not Tithes, gleabe Lands, Eaſter reckonings, Midſummer dues, old Maſs houſes, Schools, and Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, and their Mortuaries, and their Tenths, ſet up by the Law of men ſince the dayes of the Apoſtles, The Magiſtrates Tenths, out of the Tenths? now was not this ſet up by the Law of men? And as men come into the fear of God, and deny themſelves, and know the Churches ſtate, as it was among the Apoſtles, by the power of God, throw down all theſe things again, ſet up by the Law of men, ſince the falſe church hath been up, Beaſt, Dragon, and falſe prophets, and the True Church in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: do you think ſhe ſhall not come out of the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs again? And the Man-child Rule, who was dead, and is alive, and Lives for evermore?</p>
               <p>And another thing Doctor <hi>Burgeſs</hi> mentions; They ſold their Lands, and laid them down at the Apoſtles feet.</p>
               <p>Where did ever any of the Prieſts, and teachers (got up fince the dayes of the Apoſtles, made by the will of men) any of their hearers do ſo to them, as they did to the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, which was in the power of God, which opens their hearts, and as I ſaid before, brought them out of the Ninths? They muſt come into the power which brings people out of the Ninths before they do ſo, for the Law brought up Tenths; and I will make the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:47471:18"/>Tenths of the earth ſerve the Strangers, Widows, and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſs, and Prieſts, that muſt change, and could not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue, becauſe of death, which the everlaſting Prieſt ends them, which everlaſting Prieſt remains, which brings people out of the Ninths; and there the Myſtery of God is known, which ends all types, figures, and ſhadows, and parables, in which they all end.</p>
               <p>For theſe that ſay they are Miniſters of the Goſpel, and have the Gleabes, Eaſter reckonings, Midſummer dues, and Tenths, and have the Augmentations provided for them, how do theſe plant Vineyards, and tread out the Corn, and Plough, and Threſh in hope, to be made partakers of their hope, and ſow Spiritual, and keep carnal? None of all this need be, if they were ſuch Miniſters, that planted Vineyards, and ſowed Spirituals, and taught the Word of God which was in the beginning, which opens the hearts of people.</p>
               <p>Thou ſayeſt in thy ſeventh page, that Gleabes is not to be ſold from the Churches, but they muſt be employed for the maintenance of the Miniſters of the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yes, for they are ſet up by the Popes, both by the old Maſs-houſes, and the Gleabes, and maintains them idle, with other things given to them, and keeps them from labouring, threſhing and ploughing, who hath rave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from the Spirit of God, and went forth from the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, ſo from the Spiritual weapons they ſhould work withal, but onely the earthly tools ſet up earthly Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and Schools, and Colledges, to make Miniſters, which is not the Temple of God, the old Maſs-houſes Eaſt and Weſt, with a croſs on the end of it, which were made by men, and not by the W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll of God.</p>
               <p>But them that witneſs their bodies the Temple of God, and comes to the power the Apoſtles were in: denies the old Maſs-houſes, which inwardly raveners have invented, and denies them that are made by the will of man, they do that are made by the Will of God, and preacheth forth freely, as they have received freely; Though they have power to eat, and power to drink, yet in many places they will not uſe their power, them that plant Vineyards, and eat of the milk of the Flock, and keeps the Goſpel with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:47471:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>charge: but why do the Miniſters made by the will of men, ſay that the people are carnal, in their Petitions, and in their writings, and yet will have means of the carnal people, and Petition the Magiſtrate for means from them, and ſue them in Courts for it? they ſhould eat of the milk of the Flock; but is not this to ſhew that they wreſt the Scriptures, and make it ſerve their own ends?</p>
               <p>And ſince the True Church went into the Wilderneſs, they ſet up their Steeple-houſe to be one; and ſince the True Croſs, the power of God hath been loſt, they have ſet up a wooden one, on the top of it.</p>
               <p>And ſince the True Miniſters hath been loſt, which were made by the Will of God, they have ſet up Schools, and Colledges, to make Miniſters in their own wills; and ſince the Power of God hath been loſt, which is the Goſpel, they have put the four Books <hi>Matthew, Mark, Luke,</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> for the Goſpel; the falſe prophets, that inwardly ravened, that got the ſheeps cloathing, have put that for the Goſpel, and went forth from the power of God; the Goſpel being inwardly ravened.</p>
               <p>And ſince the Word of God hath been loſt from man, they have put the Scripture for it, the Words of God; as in <hi>Exodus</hi> God ſpake all theſe Words, and every Word of God is pure, ſaith the Prophet; and he that addeth to theſe Words, ſaith <hi>John</hi> in the <hi>Revelations</hi> and my Words ſaith Chriſt; not the Word of God ſo the Words of God are the Scriptures of truth learnt of God; but Chriſt is the Word, which was in the beginning, before the Words were ſpoken: who comes to fulfil the Words of God, in whom they end.</p>
               <p>And ſince men hath ravened from the Spirit of God, which ſhould offer Spiritual offerings; they invented theſe Eaſter reckonings, Midſummer dues, and ſuch like: but now are they diſcovered.</p>
               <p>And the cry hath been in this great City, by Beaſt, Dragon, and falſe prophets, great Whore, and the teachers under her, and profeſſors; prophecy is ceaſed, Revelation is ceaſed; And how ſhould they ſay, Revelation was ſtanding, or Prophecy ſtanding? When they are
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:47471:19"/>inwardly ravened from the Spirit of God, which doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire, and reveal, And to hear the voice of God; there is no ſuch thing now, cry people; Now how ſhould they hear the voice of God, who are inwardly ravened? So no Miniſters made by the will of God now, but by men, by Schooles, and Colledges.</p>
               <p>But who are come to the ſpirit of God, they ravened from, knowes revelation, and inſpiration, and hearing of Gods voice, and not of men, nor by men are they made Miniſters, but by the Revelation of Jeſus, as the Apoſtles witneſſed, and are come to that, which hath gotten the great Whore, Myſtery <hi>Babylon,</hi> Beaſt, Dragon, falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, betwixt them and the Apoſtles, with the power of God, and are come over them with the power, that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles was in; Glory in the Higheſt for ever.</p>
               <p>And ſo when they inwardly ravened, and went from Chriſt the Everlaſting Prieſt, they ſet up other Prieſts made by men, and heard them, inſtead of Chriſt; and when they inwardly ravened, and went from the Apoſtles, from the annointing within, which did teach them, and needed none other to teach them, but as the ſame annointing did teach them, to continue in the Son, and in the Father: ſo not in the Peace, Chriſt the Peace, but are ſuch as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy, and worry one another about Eaſter reckonings, Midſummer dues, Tithes, and Stipends, and Augmenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and worry their Hearers for Tenths; ſuch are like them that <hi>Micah</hi> ſpoke of, in the third chapter, That brings people all on heaps, that muſt be ploughed up like a field, out of the Apoſtles Power and Doctrine, out of the Prophet <hi>Micahs</hi> Spirit.</p>
               <p>The firſt Prieſt-hood, was a type of the everlaſting Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood Chriſt Jeſus, the law without, a figure of the Law within, the firſt covenant was a figure of the everlaſting co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, which firſt covenant, ſtood in types, ſhadowes, and figures, for the bringing in of a better hope; ſo we witneſſe the better hope come in, and the end of the other; and the offerings in the firſt Prieſt-hood was a figure of Chriſt, the everlaſting offering, who offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up himſelf through the eternal ſpirit, and ended the other.</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:47471:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Circomciſſion without, a figure of circumciſion within, and the law written in Tables of ſtone without, I will write them upon their hearts, and ſtone, upon ſtone, and the engraving, and will cut out the graving thereof, ſaith the Lord, and Chriſt is called the ſtone.</p>
               <p>And the Temple without was a figure of Chriſt, who was the Temple of God, and the Saints were made the Temples of God, in whom he would dwell and makes his abode.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> without, of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> which comes down out of heaven; and the blood of bulls and goats, a figure of the blood of Jeſus Chriſt the Son of God, which takes away ſin, which the blood of bulls and goats could not; and the one offering which perfects for ever them that are ſanctified, which the other offerings could not, which this offering doth, and they need no more.</p>
               <p>So Chriſt, the Tenple of God, ſaid, The Temple ſhould be thrown down, and not one ſtone left upon another; who ends the offerings, ends the firſt Covenant.</p>
               <p>Now minde the ſix dayes of leavened bread, and the ſeventh of reſt; and mind the tenths in the fall, man drove from God, in the earth, the Law of the firſt prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and war; and minde the everlaſting prieſthood, that redeems people out of the earth, ends the war.</p>
               <p>And the Sabbath was given for a ſigne to the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> after the fall from the righteouſneſſe, and the i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of God; the man ſervant, the maid ſervant, Ox, and Aſſe, and all within his gates might reſt, not bear a burthen, not gather meat that day, nor make a fire throughout all their congregations; now mind the ſtate of the creatures, how all was oppreſſed, Ox, Aſſe, and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants; and the Lord gave his Sabbath for a ſign, ſo the Jewes Sabbath is a day, the ſign, of ſomething, of reſt, of Chriſt the reſt to the whole creation, Ox, and Aſſe, and ſervant and ſtranger.</p>
               <p>So he was accuſed of them, that had the ſign, to be a Sabbath breaker, ſo new moones, meats, and drinks, and and holy dayes, are ſhadows of good things to come, but the body is Chriſt; ſo who knowes Chriſt the body, ſees
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:47471:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>before new moons was, meats, drinks, or Sabbath-dayes and witneſſeth the end of the ſhadowes, and can ſay, that the good thing is come, ſo the Chriſtian Sabbath is Chriſt who was before dayes was, before the World was made, glorified with the Father before the World began:</p>
               <p>And who is in him, need not go forth to gather his meat, nor to make a fire nor bear a burthen, for Chriſt is his reſt, and much more, is to be ſaid in this which is hard to be uttered.</p>
               <p>And the Saints meet together on the firſt day of the week, and many things I have to declare, which as yet is hard to be uttered, but the day is dawning, the dew of heaven is known, the morning ſtar is broken forth; and the Lord is riſen, and Chriſt is come to reign, he that was dead, is alive, and lives for evermore, and the Lamb and the Saints ſhall have the victory.</p>
               <p>So ſeeing Doctor, thou that wouldeſt keep up Tythes, and down with Biſhops laws, he that ſet up one, ſet up the other, and all power, Eaſter-reckonings, and Midſummer-dues, muſt come down together, if thou deny thy ſelf intereſt, and waſt in the power of God, with which thou might ſee, what is got up ſince the dayes of the Apoſtles, and with which power, thou mighteſt ſee, what power they were in.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>This from a lover of thy Soul, and all your Souls, and Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal good, who is in that, and lives, and reigns in that, which was in the Beginning, G. F.</signed>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <p>The <hi>Doctor</hi> ſaid, He did not take notice of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry falſe report upon his own perſon, but upon the Miniſtry it ſelf.</p>
                  <p>But who hath been, and are the greateſt reporters even the Prieſts, the falſe Miniſters, who have got up ſince the dayes of the Apoſtles.</p>
               </postscript>
               <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:47471:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
